Guide to the William Wallace Booth Papers, 1922-1973 AIS.1973.23
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- University of Pittsburgh, 1922-1973; 1941-1968; 1.
  - Subject Files, 1934-1973; VI.
    - Memoranda, 8.
      - 1963-1967 (Box 9, Folder 203)
        - Stanton C. Crawford appointed acting chancellor, August 6, 1963; 6.
        - "Comments on Planning in a University," no author, 7.
        - Endowment Fund investigation by Finance Committee, June 13,1966; 8.
        - "Engineering Defense Training", circa 1942; 9.
        - Contracts with Federal Agencies, 10.
        - The University of Pittsburgh Three Year Plan For Victory, 11.
        - Graduate Center for Public Works Engineering and Administration, a draft proposal, February 1, 1967; 12.
      - 1955-1967 (Box 9, Folder 204)
        - IBM, Financing the new 7070 system, June 2, 1960; 1.
        - Law School - change of name for earned degree, 2.
        - National Endowment for the Humanities, first public statement concerning plans prepared for press release by NEH Chairman Dr. H.A. Moe, March 20, 1066; 3.
        - O'Hara Parking Garage - acquisition of title by the university, 4.
        - The Organization of the University of Pittsburgh a report by Heald, Hobson, and Associates, to the Board of Trust, 7/17/67Acquisition and management of Ruskin Apartments, August 27, 1965; 5.
        - Reorganization of the University Administration, September 15, 1967; 6.
        - Edwin Rund in regards to cash donation to the university from the Edwin Rund Estate, 7.
        - Allan Scaife, President Board of Trust, regarding laudatory comments on the man chosen to succeed Chancellor Fitzgerald; includes a memoranda prepared by Dr. Litchfield on General Policy Questions, June 10, 1955; 8.
        - "Ten Year Objectives", 9.
        - Mr. M.S. Unger - offer to the university to purchase 5090 Warwick Terrace, 10.
    - Pitt-Wildwood Club, 9.
      - Correspondence, 1956-1960 (Box 9, Folder 205)
        Regarding asking William Wallace Booth to attend the organizational, October 3, 1956. Meeting of the Pitt Wildwood Club; also points out that the club property was donated by Mrs. Scaife. T.J. Hamilton's (club administrator) recommendations for operating the club, October 8, 1957. Hamilton to Litchfield urging promotion of non-university membership in order to make the club sustain itself, March 4, 1958. Hamilton to Litchfield in regards to a request by Hamilton to be relieved of his duties because his recommendations were not followed, March 27, 1958. Personal letter to William Wallace Booth from Hamilton, then Executive Director of the Athletic Association of Western Universities, containing a comment regarding the sale of PWC, January 20, 1960. Organization for Governing and Administering Pitt Wildwood Club. Stone Lodge (Successor to the PWC) request to postpone payments to the university, January 22, 1964.
    - Wesley Posvar, 10.
      - Speech - "The University and the Student in a Changing Society," commencement address at Miami (of Ohio) University, December 22, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 206)
    - Acquisition of Schenley Park Apartments and Hotel, 11.
      - Apartments, 1955-1956 (Box 9, Folder 207)
        - Board of Trustees meeting minutes, discussion of purchase begins on page 110, December 22, 1955; 1.
        - Closing of purchase; minutes of the last meeting of the directors of the Schenley Park Apartments Company and election of new directors representing the university, January 3, 1956; 2.
        - Resolutions expressing appreciation to Leon Falk and Hartwell Hillman for their help in purchasing apartments, January 30, 1956; 3.
      - Hotel, 1956 (Box 9, Folder 208-209)
        - Agreement to purchase the hotel, February 3, 1956; 1.
        - Board of Trustees meeting minutes at which the purchase was discussed; docket and resolutions from same meeting discussed, February 14, 1956; 2.
        - Petition for review of Pennsylvania Capital Stock Tax account of the Schenley Park Apartments Company, 1956; 3.
    - State Relationship for the University, 12.
      - 1965 (Box 9, Folder 210)
        - Resolution of the B/T to request an additional appropriation from the Commonwealth, June 2, 1965; 1.
        - Letter from the international vice president of the Building Service Employees Union to the governor supporting the university's request for additional money, June 9, 1965; 2.
        - The impending Ford Foundation study press release in regards to the university's financial needs, June 7, 1965; 3.
        - Letter in regards to Greater Pittsburgh Conference urging the Commonwealth to appropriate the money requested by Pitt, June 15, 1965; 4.
        - Letter urging that the North-Stadium and Community College projects be abandoned and the money for these projects be funneled to Pitt, July 30, 1965; 5.
        - House Bill No. 2 marking the university a state-related institution, July 25, 1965; 6.
    - International Studies, 13.
      - Correspondence and Memoranda, 1962-1969 (Box 9, Folder 211)
        - Correspondence - Regarding foreign student application procedure and requirements, October 22, 1962; 1.
        - Memoranda - In regards to modification of the International Relations Curriculum, February 28, 1968; 2.
        - Memoranda - In regards to establishment of the University Center for International Studies from Chancellor Posvar, August 5, 1968; 3.
        - Memoranda - In regards to formation of an International Relations Research Committee from Carl Beck, December 11, 1968; 4.
        - Memoranda - In regards to criteria for individual research grants, March 27, 1969; 5.
        - Memoranda - Statement on the desirability of inter-institutional cooperation, 6.
        - Memoranda - Directive on student designed undergraduate course in international studies, 7.
    - University Development Program Luncheon, 14.
      - Invitations and guest list, February 5, 1962 (Box 9, Folder 212)
    - University Senate, 15.
      - Annual Report 1972/73 (Box 9, Folder 213)
      - Minutes, 1967-1969 (Box 9, Folder 214)
      - Statements to the Senate in regards to state related status, proposed joint statement of the chancellor of the Board of Trustees Chairman of the Senate, February 11, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 214a)
        Statements from various university schools and departments Dentistry, Education, Graduate School of Business, Graduate School of Public Health, Grad. School of Library and Information Sciences, Medicine, Natural Sciences, Graduate School of Public and International Affairs, Humanities, Social Sciences, Speech and Theater Arts.
    - University Study Committee, 16.
      - Memoranda, minutes, and report (Box 9, Folder 215)
        Memoranda - Comments on "Progress of the University Study Committee," issued by Educational Policies Committee of the University Senate, April 28, 1965. Minutes, 1965. Report - "A Confidential Faculty Appreciation of the Situation of the Pitt Law School," August 1965.
    - Miscellaneous Files, 17.
      - Action Housing: in regards to legal opinion purpose (Box 9, Folder 216)
      - Biographies: 1. Dr. R.A. Moore; 2. G. Price; and 3. F. Rose (Box 9, Folder 217)
      - Housing and Home Finance Agency in regards to public law 214 (Box 9, Folder 218)
      - McKeesport Area Industrial Development Corporation statement of purpose (Box 9, Folder 219)
      - Newspaper clippings (Box 9, Folder 220)
      - University Administrative Chart illustrating University administrative structure, October 9, 1952 (Box 9, Folder 221)
      - University Building Fund Campaign -Memorandum on how to obtain gifts (Box 9, Folder 222)
      - University Correspondence (Box 9, Folder 223)
        - To approve by mail ballot a city ordinance allowing the University to construct a service tunnel under Forbes, September 30, 1964; 1.
        - To approve by mail ballot no. 1 the refinancing of the purchase of the Forbes Craig apt. title from Forbes Shenley Co. to the University, October 5, 1964; 2.
        - To approve by mail ballot purchase of land for dormitories at Titusville campus, March 10, 1965; 3.
        - To approve by mail ballot 1. the purchase of property for the Johnstown Campus, 2. the sale of University property in McKean County, March 25, 1966; 4.
      - Index of March 1961 University Development Projects in the Academic Disciplines (Box 9, Folder 224)
      - University Enrollment - Graphs depicting University enrollment 1921/22 through 1943/44 (Box 9, Folder 225)
      - University Faculty Memorial to Board of Trustees in regards to University's role in World War II (Box 9, Folder 226)
      - University Memo to S.C. Crawford in regards to borrowing money until state appropriations are received (Box 9, Folder 227)
      - University Real Estate Acquisitions since 1950 for Educational Purposes (Box 9, Folder 228)
      - University Retirement Plan for Faculty communications and memoranda (Box 9, Folder 229)
        Most of the correspondence is between Booth and individual faculty, and administrators concerning their particular retirement security.
        - "Retirement Plan for Members of the Faculty Professional, and Administrative Staffs," recommended by the University Senate, April 6, 1946; 1.
        - List of "Retired Faculty Members still living at December 31, 1956", 2.
        - "Proposed Adjustments of the Supplementary Retirement Allowances to the Group of Older Faculty Members", 3.
        - Memorandum from Dr. Litchfield to the Board of Trustees concerning modification from the University's retirement plan for faculty (also contains a brief history of the various retirement plans since their inception in 1919), March 7, 1957; 4.
      - University Selected Policy papers and statements, October 10, 1961 (Box 9, Folder 230)
      - University Space agency proposal to locate a space development (research) center in Oakland (Box 9, Folder 231)
      - "Standard Practice Procedures for the Handling and Protection of Classified Matter of the Dept. of Defense", December 12, 1966 (Box 9, Folder 232)
      - Termination of the University's "Program of Collaboration." Joint statement of Chancellor Posvar and Dr. Juan I. Lovato Rector of the Central University of Ecuador (Box 9, Folder 233)
      - University Long-range Development Plans, February 15, 1961 (Box 9, Folder 234)
- Oakland Corporation, 1961-1966; 2.
  The Oakland Corporation was a private development company formed by six non-profit education groups in the Oakland area of Pittsburgh: the Carnegie Institute of Technology, Carnegie Institute, Mellon Institute, the Roman Catholic Diocese of Pittsburgh, Mt. Mercy College, and the University of Pittsburgh. The corporation was designed to preserve and develop the urban university-cultural areas in Pittsburgh. Booth joined the Oakland Corporation circa 1961 where he served as an officer and director.
  The Oakland Corporation subgroup includes administrative and organizational records, biographical/historical sketches, correspondence, financial reports, legislative acts, memoranda, and newspaper clippings.
  - Organization and Administration, 1962-1966; I.
    - Memorandum of organization, Articles of Incorporation, By-laws (Box 9, Folder 234A)
    - Annual Reports, 1962-1963 (Box 9, Folder 235)
    - Minutes, 1962-1966 (Box 9, Folder 235A)
  - Correspondence, 1962-1965; II.
    - 1962 (Box 9, Folder 236)
      - In regards to a loan from Prudential Life Insurance Co., 1.
      - From New England Lire Insurance Co. expressing interest in financing the Oakland Corporation and requesting citations from Pa. law regarding urban renewal, March 22, 1962; 2.
      - To the Assistant Chancellor for Business Affairs to certify the university had bought 250 OC shares, May 16, 1962; 3.
      - Letter from Emerson and Company (financial advisors) in regards to the value of Oakland Corporation real estate investments relative to the pending request or the Kennedy administration to eliminate the accelerated depreciation allowances on real estate investments. Also a discussion of the university's negotiations with the Greek Catholic Union for the purchase of the Flannery Building property, June 11. 1962; 4.
      - Letter from E.S. Emerson of Emerson and Co. in regards to financing Oakland Corporation projects; noting that these projects fall into two broad categories: 1. those of a nonprofit nature which can be federally funded; 2. "other activities" There is a lengthy discussion of each. This letter was sent to the URA in the form of a question asking about the policy of the GSA and URA relative to buying and leasing land, building or selling redeveloped property to the Oakland Corporation The basic question concerned whether such transactions would quality for tax exemptions under section 112 of the Housing and Home Finance Agency. The reply of Theodore L. Hazlet, Jr. URA general counsel on August 29 follows, August 1962; 5.
      - From E.S. Emerson in regards to postponing request for tax exempt status under section 112. Further discussion of ideas in regards to tax exempt status, October 26, 1962; 6.
    - 1963-1965 (Box 9, Folder 237)
      - Letter in regards to proposed legislation and meeting local representatives to the Pennsylvania General Assembly to clear the air rights for the Panther-Hollow project, May 2, 1963; 1.
      - That the Oakland Corporation will host the monthly meeting of the Executive Committee of the Allegheny Conference on Community Development at which the plans for the Panther Hallow research facility would be revealed, May 8, 1963; 2.
      - Invitation to Booth to be present for dinner at Carnegie Music Hall, June 10, when the corporation's plans for a research park are previewed for civic, government and business leaders, May 10, 1963; 3.
      - Letter of transmittal to Mellon Bank and a resolution accepting credit offered by the same bank, March 25, 1964; 4.
      - Letter in regards to procedure to follow in acquiring a portion of Schenley Park and city property being held for Carnegie Tech (now CMU), April 1, 1964; 5.
      - Letter from Oakland Corporation General Manaeer, Frank Nowak, suggesting a tie in with the Bellefield System to supply heat and air conditioning for the buildings, October 12. 1964; 6.
      - May 4, 1965: Letter of transmittal from Nowak to Booth forwarding a proposal from Charles Luckman Associates, planning and architectural advisors and consultants. This proposal regarded professional services in regards to overall design and leases, i.e. finding tenants,Letter from R.M. Bradley & Company expressing indignation over the fact that Cushman & Wakefield, Realtors had been hired to make a feasibility study of the Panther Hallow project. Bradley protested that it had already made the study without charging a fee and pointed that Cushman & Wakefield had been offered $10,000. In such case Bradley suggested it was "terribly used," and suggested that C & W was hired because Bradley protectedthe interests of the University, August 18, 1965; 7.
  - Memoranda, 1962-1966; III.
    - 1962-1963 (Box 9, Folder 238)
      - In regards to a legal opinion that the university as a nonprofit corporation does not have the authority to guarantee the financial obligations of Oakland Corporation. This opinion was sent to Booth by J.H. White. White's occupation is not identified, February 26, 1962; 1.
      - From E.S. Emerson in regards to a discussion (explanation) of common stock subscriptions to Oakland Corporation, May 10, 1962; 2.
      - In regards to purchase of the Olander Property at the corner of Dithridge and Henry Streets, July 3, 1962; 3.
      - Enclosed in a letter of transmittal from Lawrence Monnet to Booth. The original memoranda had been sent to Chancellor Litchfield from E.S. Emerson, financial advisor and consultant in regards to that "... it is both possible and desirable to qualify Oakland as an Eligible Private Development Corporation under section 112 of the Housing Act of 1961"Contains a lengthy explanation to buttress this opinion, July 6, 1962; 4.
      - In regards to the advisability that Oakland Corporation not be closely identified (publically) with the university although this is in fact the case, September 20, 1962; 5.
      - To Dr. Litchfield, suggested agenda for the January 9, 1963 Board of Directors meeting in regards to financial matters, January 4, 1963; 6.
      - In regards to increasing the number of board members and the election of Fred Smith to the board, February 13, 1963; 7.
      - In regards to "air rights" from the Panther Hallow protect from Oakland Corporation's legal counsel, William P. Hackney, March 15, 1963; 8.
      - In regards to Pennsylvania law concerning the taxation of air rights, April 16, 1963; 9.
      - In regards to an outline of the financing plan worked out with Equitable Fire Insurance Co. for the Panther Hollow project.December 30, 1963Reproduction of several sections of an article by George R. Herbert, President of the Research Triangle Institute in North Carolina. Herbert discusses the laboratory and environmental factors necessary for a research park, June 13, 1963; 10.
    - 1964-1966 (Box 9, Folder 239)
      - A caution against premature publicity which may harm the project, February 4, 1964; 1.
      - A discussion the reason financial credits available under section 112 of the HHFA can no longer be obtained and there is further discussion of financing of the Panther Hollow project. Reference is made that outside groups are interested in financing the project, but that the corporation was still hoping that two Pittsburgh based firms would come into partnership with the corporation, February 13, 1964; 2.
      - In regards to a loan having been secured from Mellon Bank to finance land acquisition, March 13, 1964; 3.
      - In regards to "Facts Concerning the Mellon Bank Loan", March 20, 1964; 4.
      - Covering three items: acquiring land through the URA; the US Steel proposal; and acquiring as easement over land owned by the Bureau of Mines, April 2, 1964; 5.
      - Cost analysis of the first Panther Hollow project in regards to profit or loss to Oakland Corporation and a question of whether the corporation will lack enough real interest in the building. (This memorandum is in response to a memorandum by M.C. Conick, a member of the Board of Directors. Mr. Conick's memorandum which follows is an analysis of an "Economic Study of Panther Hollow" Stage 1, Phase 1, March 1964), April 23, 1964; 6.
      - In regards to financing and leasing the first building in Panther Hollow, August 13, 1964; 7.
      - Marked personal and confidential to Booth from R.M. Bradley and Co. outlining the firms efforts on behalf of Oakland Corporation, January 20, 1965; 8.
      - Schedule of finishes for the first building in Panther Hollow, September 21, 1965; 9.
      - From William P. Hackney to Booth in regards to the various legal status Oakland Corporation may assume upon becoming a non-profit organization, March 23, 1966; 10.
  - Financial Reports, 1962-1965; IV.
    - Financial statements, reports, projections, balance sheets, and audits, 1962-1965 (Box 9, Folder 240)
  - Subject Files, 1961-1964; V.
    - Biographical sketches (Box 9, Folder 241)
      - Edwin Hodge, Jr. President of Pittsburgh Forgings Company, 1.
      - Frank L. Magee, 2.
      - Frederick Maurice Smith, Oakland Corporation President, 3.
    - Cooperation and Conveyance Agreement, 1962 (Box 9, Folder 242)
      Between the city of Chicago, the University of Chicago, and the South West Park Neighborhood Redevelopment Corporation. This legal document was used to illustrate how cooperation between, the city, a private non-profit organization, and educational institution can be implemented to redevelop the area around the institution. This draft is dated March 2, 1962.
    - Craig Street Disposal of property at 511 (Box 9, Folder 243)
      Memoranda to the Board of Directors setting forth the proposals of the parties interested in the property. The memoranda asked that the board members decide on a buyer and were reminded that disposal of the property "...is the only remaining obstacle preventing final liquidation of the corporation."
    - Howard Johnson Deal, 1962-1963 (Box 9, Folder 244)
      In regards to negotiations to purchase and erect a motor lodge (Note, this material is arranged chronologically according to the progression of the negotiations): Memo, August 2, 1962 - From E.S. Emerson, financial consultant to Oakland Corporation, to the University treasurer, setting forth his thoughts on the proposed motor inn, commenting on the financial and operating plans, and projecting as to its function in the scheme of Oakland after the district is redeveloped. (See Emerson's letter of August 7 to which this memo was attached). September 21, 1962 - In regards to that the university finance committee wants more time before buying and leasing the property; that the Oakland Corporation has definitely decided not to invest its funds in the project; but that the developers plan to proceed with the building of the motor lodge and plan to contact the university at a future date. Memo, November 21, 1962 - In regards to rental received by the university from the motor lodge will not be subject to taxes. Opinion of W.P. Hackeny to William Wallace Booth. Letter, December 28, 1962 - In regards to length of lease and terms of rental. Letter of transmittal January 21, 1963 - In regards to min. of the university finance Committee at which the HJ Deal was discussed; and the "Purchase and Lease of Proposed HJ Motor Lodge," as mentioned in the minutes are attached. Memo, January 29, 1963 - In regards to caution in amending the plan site which might cause disapproval by the City Planning Commission. Memo, February 8, 1963 - In regards to the university would buy the property only if the rental income were non-taxable to the university. Letter of transmittal, February 26, 1963 - In regards to a draft of the "Covenants and Waiver of Damages." Memo, March 19, 1963 - In regards to money to be drawn on the university's endowment fund for site purchase. Undated legal documents: The agreement (unexecuted) between the Oakland Corporation and Minute Car Wash Corporation, the property owner Covenants and Waiver of Damages by Minute Car Wash Corporation (Whereby the car wash corporation waivered damages for itself, its heirs and assigns if the city altered the road pattern in the vicinity of the property.
    - Economic Study of Panther Hollow - Stage 1, Phase 1, March 1964 (Box 9, Folder 245)
    - City of Pittsburgh, Department of Planning, "A Staff Report on Industrial Research Park Development in or near the Oakland District", October 1962 (Box 9, Folder 246)
      Urges the adoption of one of three possible sites: Bates Street, both sides, south of the Boulevard of the Allies; Soho District and Saline Street Valley. Statement on the need for an industrial park maps.
    - Prospectus - "The ABC Development Corporation" subtitled, "A Proposed Corporation to aid in the redevelopment of the Oakland area of the City of Pittsburgh", October 1961 (Box 9, Folder 247)
      This Corporation finally selected the name Oakland Corporation
    - Prospectus, 1961-1962 (Box 9, Folder 248)
      - Preliminary Prospectus Oakland Corporation, December 11, 1961; 1.
      - Preliminary Prospectus Oakland Corporation, January 22, 1962; 2.
      - Prospectus Oakland Corporation, March 1962; 3.
    - Senate Bill 522 (Box 9, Folder 249)
      In regards to giving person other than owner's estates rights in non-contiguous air above the surface of the ground - Pennsylvania Securities Act.
    - United States Steel Proposal, 1964 (Box 9, Folder 250)